Oliver Tambo Papers 2000.0144
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Series C: Special Topics
  - Subjects (Box C5)
    - Churches (Box C5., Folder 2)
      - World Council of Churches ( WCC) (Box C5., Folder 2.4)
        - Correspondence between Rev. Joan B. Campbell (Executive Director, United States Office, WCC) and Thabo Mbeki re the delegation meeting with the ANC, 1986
        - Reports
          - WCC Executive Committee decision to support organisations combating racism, (Church reactions/profiles on recipient organisations - Frelimo/ PAIGC ( Partido Africano de Independencia da Guinea e Cabo Verde), 1970 September
          - The WCC and International Banking in Southern Africa Central Committee, West-Berlin, 1974 August 11 - 18
        - Miscellaneous (2 items)
        - Publications (3 items)
          - "Challenge to the Churches," report of a Consultation on The Church and the Liberation of Southern Africa, Kitwe, Zambia, 1976 November 25 - 30
          - WCC statements and actions on racism, 1948 - 1979
          - "The Churches' Search for Justice and Peace in Southern Africa," Report on Meeting in Lusaka, 1987 May 4 - 8
    - Death Row (Box C5., Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous Report, "Victims of apartheid on Death Row,", circa 1989 February
      - News Releases (2 items)
        Stay of execution for 'Sharpeville Six'/Nadel statement on executions, 1988.
    - Detentions (Box C5., Folder 4)
      - List of Political Prisoners in South Africa prepared by International Defence and Aid Fund, 1974 September 1
      - 2nd report on arrests, detentions and trials of members and supporters of: SASO, BPC, BAWU, TECON, BCP Issued by The Program of Social Change, 1974 December 23
    - Publications (2 items) (Box C5., Folder 4)
      - ADAC News ( Detention Action Committee Newsletter): No.5, 1983 April
      - Amnesty International Circulars re Arrests, Legal Concern, Fear of Ill-Treatment of Detainees, 1990 March 23 - April 3
    - Disinvestment and Sanctions (See also: Special Topics - Oil Embargo) (Box C5., Folder 5)
      - Correspondence (1 item) (Box C5., Folder 5.1)
        Evidence of US firms violating the trade embargo directed against South Africa, 1986.
      - ANC Sanctions folder (Box C5., Folder 5.2)
        Items include Correspondence between Gill Marcus and Johnny Makatini, 1986; "The people of South Africa call for sanctions," "Impose sanctions to assist the people of South Africa's fight for freedom," "Economic sanctions and the boycott of South African goods."
      - Reports (Box C5., Folder 5.3)
        - Brief on exposés of British business in South Africa, ANC, 1973 March 28
        - The economic impact of sanctions against South Africa, Starnberger Institute, 1987 July
        - Summary of Starnberger study
      - Speeches, Papers, Policy Documents (Box C5., Folder 5.4)
        - "Economic sanctions against South Africa," a policy document based on the Study Conference on Sanctions against South Africa, prepared by J. Symonds, Anti-Apartheid Movement, UK, 1962 June 23
        - International Conference on Sanctions against South Africa, points for working paper on the Declaration, 1981 April 4
        - "Sanctions: The Path to Peaceful Change," Address by Shridath S. Ramphal (Commonwealth Secretary-General) to the World Conference on Sanctions against Racist South Africa, Paris, 1986 June 16
        - "Working paper by the chairman of the Preparatory Committee for the Declaration of The World Conference on Sanctions against Racist South Africa,", 1986 June 16 - 20
      - Statements (Box C5., Folder 5.5)
        - "The Case for Mandatory Economic Sanctions Against South Africa," ANC, 1981
        - Text of statement by Abdul S. Minty to a closed session of the Security Council Committee on the arms embargo against South Africa, "Anti-Apartheid World Campaign against military and nuclear collaboration with South Africa,", 1983 September 23
        - Academic Contacts with South Africa, M. P. K. Sorrenson, Professor of History, University of Auckland, 1985 March 29
        - Sanctions, Frene Ginwala, London, 1990 March 17
      - Publications (Box C5., Folder 5.6)
        - ANC President Oliver Tambo Calls for Sanctions
        - Barclays Shadow Report, 1981-1984
      - Miscellaneous (Box C5., Folder 5.7)
        - Bills, United Kingdom
    - Elections, before 1990 (Box C5., Folder 6)
      - Reports (6 items)
    - Labour Matters (Box C5., Folder 7)
      - Circulars, Reports, Papers (6 items)
        - Permanent Secretariat of the African Committee for Union Coordination and Action against Apartheid and Colonialism (Circular No.03/74)
        - Report on Seminar "Profile of Black Skills, Manpower Distribution, Education and Skills Training in South Africa,", 1988 July 19 - 20
        - Mosebetsi: The Story of a South African Worker (Vuyisile Mini)
        - Appeal to the Black Workers of South Africa on their struggle for demands for higher wages, trade union rights and better conditions of life and work
    - Military and Defence (Box C5., Folder 8)
      - Appeal, White Paper, Publications, Press Cuttings (6 items)
        - Appeal: International Conference against Imperialist Military Bases in the Indian Ocean and for making Indian Ocean a zone of peace, New Delhi, 1974 August 27 - 29
        - White Paper on Defence and Armaments Supply, 1982
        - Pamphlet-- National Security
        - Paratus, 1979 May
    - National Question (Box C5., Folder 9)
      - Reports and Papers (2 items)
        - " South Africa's National Question"
        - "The National Question in South Africa"
    - Oil Embargo (See also: Special Topics - Disinvestment/ Sanctions) (Box C5., Folder 10)
      - Correspondence (9 items), 1974 (Box C5., Folder 10.1)
      - Documents of the Research and Action Group on Oil: No.1 - 4, 1974 January (Box C5., Folder 10.2)
      - Miscellaneous (4 items) (Box C5., Folder 10.3)
        Items include Appeal for an Oil Embargo against South Africa; Notes taken by Oliver Tambo from the Rand Daily Mail (1985) re consequences of disinvestment.
      - Publications (3 items) (Box C5., Folder 10.4)
        - "Oil - A Weapon against Apartheid. Proposals for Action to Cut off South Africa's Supply of Oil," Paper presented at International Seminar on an Oil Embargo against South Africa, 1980 March 14 - 16
        - Secret Oil Deliveries to South Africa 1981 - 1982, Shipping Research Bureau/Amsterdam
        - Newsletter of the Oil Embargo against South Africa, 1986 May
    - Political Prisoners (Box C5., Folder 11)
      - Report--"Draft Report of the Sub-Committee for the Release of Political Prisoners"
      - Greeting Cards and Messages
        Items include Greetings to Helen Joseph on her 80 Birthday from political prisoners on Robben Island ( Nelson Mandela, A. N. Kathrada, A. Mlangeni, Walter Sisulu...).
    - South African Government (Box C5., Folder 12)
      - P. W. Botha (Box C5., Folder 12.1)
        - Correspondence (2 items) (Box C5., Folder 12.1.1)
          re Rev. Chikane's reaction to a letter sent to Archbishop Tutu by P. W. Botha, 1988 March.
        - Statements (2 items) (Box C5., Folder 12.1.2)
        - Memorandum (Box C5., Folder 12.1.3)
          EPG, Botha’s Intent and British position (30 April 1986) [includes attached press cuttings).
      - F. W. de Klerk (Box C5., Folder 12.2)
        - Correspondence (2 items) (Box C5., Folder 12.2.1)
          Items include Statement by Dirk Coetzee to F. W. de Klerk.
        - Speeches and Statements (4 items) (Box C5., Folder 12.2.2)
          Includes Statement in reaction to decision of NEC to send a delegation, 1990 February; Address by F. W. de Klerk to the Institute of Directors, London, 1991 April 23.
        - Other Comments (Box C5., Folder 12.2.3)
          - Comment/Points to note in De Klerk Speech, Frene Ginwala, London, 1990 February 7
          - Quo Vadis De Klerk?, Frene Ginwala
        - Memorandum/White Paper (Box C5., Folder 12.2.4)
          - Special Cabinet Committee: Memorandum on Constitutional Development in South Africa, 1984 August
          - The White Paper on Urbanisation
        - Speech and Statement--Other NP Ministers (Box C5., Folder 12.2.5)
          - Speech by J. C. Heunis, Minister of Constitutional Development and Planning during his budget vote in Parliament, 1989 May 5
          - "Return of Refugees," Statement by the Minister of Foreign Affairs, Mr. R. F. Botha, 1991 March 21
        - Miscellaneous (7 items) (Box C5., Folder 12.2.6)
          Includes Strategy for the expansion of the NP in Soweto and its neighbouring townships; Pamphlet-- ...and what about the BLACK PEOPLE? Dr. Stoffel van der Merwe; Proposed Plan of Action of the NP, Election, 1989 September 6.
    - Sport (Box C5., Folder 13)
      - Newsletter of the International Campaign Against Apartheid Sport and the South African Non-Racial Olympic Committee, Sport and Apartheid, Vol.1, No.5, 1989 March
    - Violence (Box C5., Folder 14)
      - Reports
        - Fire Damage Inspection Report/House in Umlazi Township, Kwa Zulu, University of Natal/Built Environment Support Group
        - Confidential Interim Report on the Violence in Natal: Commissioner Mr. Advocate R. S. Douglas
      - Statements and Resolutions
        - ANC Press Statement of the Wave of Violence, 1990 September 13
        - Resolutions of the NEC on Violence, 1990 September 18 - 19
        - Resolution arising from the report of the ANC/ COSATU National Working Committee on Violence, 1990 September 20
        - Announcement by the State President on Measures to Terminate the Violence, 1990 September 20
        - Miscellaneous Press Cutting
          - IDAF Information, No. 90, "The Natal Violence,", 1990 August 4
    - "Workers Movement" (Box C5., Folder 15)
      - The Workers Movement, SACTU and the ANC - a struggle for Marxist policies
      - South Africa's Impending Socialist Revolution - Perspective of the Marxist Workers' Tendency of the ANC (Inqaba/Ya Basebenzi publication), circa 1982 May
    - Women (Box C5., Folder 16)
      - Pamphlets (2 items)
        - Women Organised, A Fedsaw Commemorative Pamphlet
    - Subjects (Box 1)
      - Aids (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Apartheid (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Apologies for (Box 1, Folder 2a)
        - Commentaries (Box 1, Folder 2b)
        - Health Services (Box 1, Folder 2c)
        - Repeals on Apartheid Laws,Desegregation of Public Facilities (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Race Classification (Box 1, Folder 2e)
        - Assassinations, Threats and Killings (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Bill of Rights (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Church (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Civil Service (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Cold War (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Coloured Community (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Criminality (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Defiance Campaigns--Republic Day Protests, 1981, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Demographic Issues (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Destabilisation against Frontline and SADCC States (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Detentions (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Disinvestment (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - Ecology, etc. Conservation and Rural Development (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Economy (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Indian Community (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - Education in South Africa and Tanzania (See also Scholars and Students) (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - Exiles and Expatriates (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - Evolution and South Africa (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - The Future South Africa (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - Goldstone Commission (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - Homelands (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Hostels (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - Human Rights (Box 1, Folder 25)
        - Hunger Strikes (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - Information Scandal (Box 1, Folder 27)
        - Liberals (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - Liberation Broadcasters (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - Local Government (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - Media/Censorship (Box 1, Folder 31)
        - Mining Industry (Box 1, Folder 32)
        - Negotiations/Constitutional (Box 1, Folder 33)
        - Non Governmental Organisations (NGOs) (Box 1, Folder 34)
          - Nuclear Arms (Box 1, Folder 34a)
        - Oil (Box 1, Folder 35)
        - Police and Prisoners Civil Rights Union, etc. (Box 1, Folder 36)
        - Police (Box 1, Folder 37)
        - Political Leaders (Box 1, Folder 38)
        - Political Prisoners and Juveniles (Box 1, Folder 39)
        - Prisons (Box 1, Folder 40)
        - Privatisation (Box 1, Folder 41)
        - Radio SA Commentaries (Box 1, Folder 42)
        - Racism, Global Struggles vs (Box 1, Folder 43)
        - Resettlement (Box 1, Folder 44)
        - Resistance, Townships (Box 1, Folder 45)
        - Right Wing (Box 1, Folder 46)
        - Sanctions (Box 1, Folder 47)
          - Vol.1 Mandela in UK, 1990 July (Box 1, Folder 47a)
            - Mandela and IRA, 1990 July
          - Vol.2 Mandela in Africa, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 47b)
            - Mandela in India, 1990
            - Mandela in Japan, 1990-1991
          - Vol.3 United States - Mandela’s visits (Box 1, Folder 47c)
            - Various articles, 1981-1986, 1991
          - Vol.4 EEC (Box 1, Folder 47)
          - Vol.5 Commonwealth (Box 1, Folder 47e)
          - Vol.6 OAU and OCOWAS (Box 1, Folder 47)
          - Vol.7 De Klerk's Travels, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 47g)
          - Vol.8 Cultural Boycott (Box 1, Folder 47h)
          - Vol.9 Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 47i)
        - Self Defence Units (Box 1, Folder 48)
        - Security Guards (Civilian) (Box 1, Folder 49)
        - Security Legislation (Box 1, Folder 50)
        - SADCC ( Southern African Development Coordination Conference) (Box 1, Folder 51)
        - Sport (Box 1, Folder 52)
        - Squatters (Box 1, Folder 53)
        - States of Emergencies, 1986 June, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 54)
        - Students and Scholars (See: Education) (Box 1, Folder 55)
        - Spy Networks/Rightwing Killings/Third Force/Harms Commission (See: Right Wing) (Box 1, Folder 56)
        - Tribalism (Box 1, Folder 57)
          - United Front, Moves towards (Box 1, Folder 57a)
        - Violence: Cape and OFS (Box 1, Folder 58)
        - Violence: Natal, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 59)
          - Violence, Transvaal (Subfile: Alexandra) (Box 1, Folder 59a)
        - Violence, The Politics of (Box 1, Folder 60)
        - Violence and Traditional Weapons (Box 1, Folder 61)
        - Violence, ANC Ultimatum to De Klerk, 1991 April (Box 1, Folder 62)
        - White Poverty (Box 1, Folder 63)
        - White Women (Box 1, Folder 64)
        - Workers/Trade Unions (Box 1, Folder 65)
          - Farm Workers (Box 1, Folder 65a)
          - Mine Workers (Box 1, Folder 65b)
      - Countries (Box 2)
        - Africa: Ethiopia; Eritrea; Zaire; Congo; Senegal; Somalia (Box 2, Folder 1)
          - Ghana; Liberia; Nigeria; Sudan (Box 2, Folder 1a)
        - Africa, South Africa’s role in (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Angola (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Australasia (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Eastern Block Countries (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - Indian Ocean Area (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - Kenya (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - Middle East (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - Mozambique (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - Namibia (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - Netherlands (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - Nordic Countries (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - South Africa (Box 2, Folder 14)
          - Links with Latin America (Box 2, Folder 14a)
          - Independent States (Box 2, Folder 14b)
        - Soviet Union (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - Swaziland (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - United Kingdom (Box 2, Folder 16a)
          - War Graves - Natal (Box 2, Folder 16aa)
          - British Labour Party (Box 2, Folder 16ab)
          - Margaret Thatcher's visit to South Africa (Box 2, Folder 16ac)
        - Zambia (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Zimbabwe (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Individuals (Box 3)
        - Apartheid Presidents--Verwoerd, Vorster, Botha (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Buthelezi, Mangosuthu G. (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - De Klerk, F. W. (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - Hani, Chris (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Mandela, Nelson (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - Mandela, Winnie (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - Sisulu Family (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - Slovo, Joe (Box 3, Folder 8)
          - Tambo, Adelaide (Box 3, Folder 8a)
        - Tambo, Oliver (Box 3, Folder 9)
          - Personal (Box 3, Folder 9.1)
          - 1971, 1980-1990 (General) (Box 3, Folder 9.2)
          - Copies of Nhân Dân, Vietnam visit of Oliver Tambo, 1978 October (Box 3, Folder 9.2a)
          - USA Visit, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9b)
        - Various press articles re Oliver Tambo
      - Organisations (Box 4)
        - African National Congress (Box 4, Folder 1)
          - Askari Defectors (Box 4, Folder 1a)
          - Camps (Box 4, Folder 1b)
          - Conference Preparation, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1c)
          - Economic/Fiscal Policies (Box 4, Folder 1)
          - Freedom Struggle (Box 4, Folder 1e)
          - Fund Raising (Box 4, Folder 1)
          - Future SA Constitution (Box 4, Folder 1g)
          - Operation Vula (Box 4, Folder 1h)
          - Organisation and Administration (Box 4, Folder 1i)
          - ANC/ SACP/ NP Relations (Box 4, Folder 1j)
          - Stay Away Protests (Box 4, Folder 1k)
          - Umkonto we Sizwe (Box 4, Folder 1l)
          - Women's League (Box 4, Folder 1m)
        - Anti-Apartheid Movement (Box 4, Folder 2)
          - United Kingdom (Box 4, Folder 2a)
          - Anti-Apartheid Youth Front (Box 4, Folder 2b)
        - ARMSCOR (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - AZAPO (Box 4, Folder 4)
        - Broederbond (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - Democratic Party (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - ECC (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Labour Party (SA) (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - National Party (Box 4, Folder 9)
          - Plans for a new Constitution (Box 4, Folder 9a)
        - OXFAM (Box 4, Folder 10)
        - Pan Africanist Congress (Box 4, Folder 11)
        - South African Communist Party ( SACP) (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - South African Defence Force ( SADF) (Box 4, Folder 13)
        - Socialist International (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - United Democratic Front ( UDF) (Box 4, Folder 15)
        - United Nations (Box 4, Folder 16)
        - World Bank (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Unsorted
- Series D: Press Cuttings, undated
    This series was not microfilmed.